Finding Aid for Phi Delta Chi, Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan) records, 1924-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Phi Delta Chi, Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan) records 1924-1995
Phi Delta Chi. Alpha Chapter. (University of Michigan).
0.4 linear feet
2013024 Bimu F41 2
Phi Delta Chi Fraternity was founded in 1883 by a group of pharmacy students at the University of Michigan. The Phi Delta Chi records contain minutes, publications, correspondence, a constitution and bylaws, a pledge manual, and photos from the mid-1990s.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the College of Pharmacy donor number ( 3112 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Phi Delta Chi Fraternity was founded on November 2, 1883, by a group of eleven University of Michigan pharmacy students, who drew up the fraternity's constitution and bylaws. These "founding fathers" of Phi Delta Chi include Charles Edward Bond, Franklin Herbert Frazee, Llewellyn Hall Gardner, Calvin Pomeroy Godfrey, Adolph Gustave Hoffman, Arthur Gilliam Hopper, Charles F. Hueber, George Pawling Leamon, Arthur Sidney Rogers, Azor Thurston, and Albert Tenney Waggoner. Albert Benjamin Prescott, Dean of the College of Pharmacy, encouraged the formation of the fraternity, served as the group's sponsor, and became the first honorary member. Because the fraternity was founded at Michigan, its chapter is the Alpha Chapter.
The fraternity was originally known as Phi Chi. Although changing the name to Phi Delta Chi was proposed at the fraternity's second meeting, it wasn't until 1910 that this name change was formally ratified. The fraternity originally accepted members from the field of chemistry as well as pharmacy. By 1933, requirements were changed to restrict membership to the field of pharmacy, and the society acquired the form in which it remains today, a professional fraternity dedicated to the field of pharmacy. Women were first inducted in 1976.
The Communicator, Phi Delta Chi's official publication, was first published in 1906 and continues to be published quarterly. Since 1883, Phi Delta Chi has chartered 57 chapters and initiated over 33,000 members.
---------------
Source: Phi Delta Chi Fraternity. "History of Phi Delta Chi." Accessed October 27, 2011. http://www.phideltachi.org/about/the-organization/19-history-of-phi-delta-chi.
The Phi Delta Chi records are divided into five series: Governance, Minutes, Miscellaneous, Photographs, and Publications.
Subjects:
Phi Delta Chi Fraternity. Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Pharmacy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Phi Delta Chi Fraternity. Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan).; University of Michigan. College of Pharmacy.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1991-2000.
Photographs.
- Governance
  The Governance series includes the Alpha Chapter's constitution and bylaws from 1987 as well as a pledge manual from 1967.
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Pledge Manual, 1967 (Box 1)
- Minutes
  The Minutes series includes meeting minutes from 1924-1930 and 1985-1986.
  - 1924-1930 (Box 1)
  - Special Meeting, 1928 (Box 1)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series is comprised of a variety of material. This includes a checkbook from the late 1940s and early 1950s, correspondence from 1930 and 1954, an early history of the fraternity, and a Certificate of Appreciation from the Salvation Army thanking the chapter for its community service during the 1993 Christmas season.
  - Checkbook, 1947-1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1930, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Early History, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Salvation Army Certificate of Appreciation, 1994 (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1994
  The Photographs series contains a ca. 1965 group photo, and negatives and prints depicting fraternity members at events in the mid-1990s.
  - Photographs (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publications series contains a 1965 issue of the Communicator, the fraternity's national publication, as well as two issues of the Alpha Tattler, the Alpha Chapter's publication, from 1992 and 1993.
  - The Alpha Tattler, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - The Communicator, 1965 (Box 1)